Finding Aid for Nathan M. Thomas Papers, 1818-1889
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nathan M. Thomas Papers 1818-1889
Thomas, Nathan M. (Nathan Macy), 1803-1887.
2 linear ft. (in three boxes) and 1 oversize folder
86178 Aa 2; UAl
Quaker abolitionist and physician in Mt. Pleasant, Ohio, and Schoolcraft, Michigan. Correspondence of Thomas, his wife Pamela S. Brown Thomas, and their children; addresses, autobiography, financial ledgers, and files relating to business activities, medical practice, and anti-slavery activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Malcolm Thomas (donor no. 867 ) in 1936 and 1939. The financial daybook and ledgers were donated by Mrs. Gordon Inglehart (donor no. 2962 ) in 1953. The Thomas autobiography was donated by Mack Thomas (donor no. 3355 ) in 1957.
The collection is open to research.
Nathan M. Thomas was born at Mount Pleasant, Jefferson Co., Ohio, on January 2, 1803, the son of Jesse and Avis (Stanton) Thomas, who were devout Quakers. He studied medicine with local practitioners and at the Medical College of Ohio in Cincinnati. In June 1830, after practicing medicine a short time in Ohio, he moved to Prairie Ronde and what would later became the village of Schoolcraft, and began a practice which continued without interruption for about twenty five years. He was married March 17, 1840, to Miss Pamela S. Brown, daughter of Thomas and Sally Brown, of Plymouth, Vermont. Four children were born to them, two sons and two daughters. Thomas would live in Schoolcraft until his death in 1887.
Although not belonging and adhering strictly to the Quakers as a sect, Thomas was staunchly opposed to slavery. In 1839, he joined a movement for the establishment of an anti-slavery paper and in 1840, he helped to form the Liberty party. In 1845, he was the Liberty party candidate for lieutenant governor of Michigan. In 1854, he was a member of the convention which organized the Republican Party in Jackson, Michigan. Prior to the abolition of slavery, Thomas's home was a haven for slaves escaping from the South to Canada. He died April 7, 1887.
The collection is divided into two series: Correspondence and Other papers: anti-slavery, medical practice, and family.
The correspondence is of Thomas, his wife Pamela S. Brown Thomas, their children Ella, Malcolm, and Stanton, and relatives, friends, public leaders, abolitionists, and publishers. These letters deal largely with family affairs, land transactions, medical discoveries, woman suffrage, the Liberty Party, and Thomas's anti-slavery activities. There are also letters of Stanton B. Thomas while a student at the University of Michigan (1859-1864) and Civil War letters of S. B. Thayer, medical director of the Merrill Horse Regiment. Other Thomas papers include manuscript addresses, essays and other papers; a manuscript autobiography of Thomas; three account books, 1832-1879, pertaining mainly to his medical practice and other business affairs. Of interest is a prospectus for a newspaper, the American Freeman, which lists Schoolcraft area subscribers.
Subjects:
Agriculture--United States.; Depressions--1836-1837--United States.; Land use--Michigan.; Liberty Party (U.S.); Medicine--Michigan.; Mount Pleasant (Jefferson County, Ohio); Ohio.; Physicians--Michigan.; Schoolcraft (Mich.); Antislavery movements--United States.; Women--Suffrage--United States.; United States. Army. Missouri Cavalry, 2nd.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; American freeman.
Contributors:
Lyon, Lucius, 1800-1851.; Birney, James Gillespie, 1792-1857.; Hussey, Erastus.; Thayer, S. B.; Thomas, Jesse O.; Thomas, Jonathan.; Thomas, Stanton Brown.; Treadwell, Seymour Boughton, 1795-1867.
- Correspondence
  - 1818-1889 and undated, 20 folders (Box 1)
- Other papers: anti-slavery, medical practice, and family
  - Ella Thomas's history of Underground Railroad with several pages of Pamela Thomas's History of Anti-Slavery (Box 1)
  - Anti-Slavery resolutions, etc. of Liberty Party, 1840s: notes, speeches, etc. N. M. Thomas on Anti-Slavery (Box 1)
  - History of Anti-Slavery Movement, 1839-1842 (Box 1)
  - Essay on medical subjects (Box 1)
  - Business Papers (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts from "The Evening Journal'' edited by Thomas (probably in Schoolcraft) (Box 1)
  - Ohio publication:Juvenile Museum, 1822 (Box 1)
  - Medical admission cards, Medical College of Ohio, 1827 medical license, 1828 and related (Box 1)
  - Memorandum book, 1832-1861 (Box 1)
    (containing accounts of notes due Thomas, Schoolcraft, Kalamazoo, Mich.)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (include land grant; carte de visite of Thomas; and letters of others)
  - Family letters, 1835 and 1841 (Box 1)
    (originals and photostats)
  - List of items removed from Nathan Thomas papers (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketch (Box 2)
  - Autobiography of Nathan M. Thomas, written in 1875 and 1886 (Box 2)
  - Day book (medical practice), 1834-1838 (Box 2)
    (include scattered later dates)
  - Ledgers (medical practice), 1832-1879, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Prospectus of the American Freeman, 1838 (Folder UAl)
    (with names of Schoolcraft area subscribers)